what's up everybody I'm coach Brett
contrast' this is coach Alex Turner and
this video is all about the Nordic
hamper
[Music]
so the nordic ham crow it's an awesome
exercise it has a ton of support in the
literature we've seen a surge in the
last decade in research on the Nordic
ham crow it's used in athletic training
all the time specifically for hamstring
strain injury prevention but more
recently we're seeing it being used in
gyms across the world for physique and
aesthetics purposes so we're gonna show
you all the ways to do it we're going to
show you regressions progressions and
we're going to show you what we do here
in the glute lab where we have everyone
doing it we're going to show you six
different ways to perform and setup
Nordiques
the first method is the partner assisted
method sterner is kneeling on an Eric's
balance pad I've got my legs behind his
feet he's dorsiflexed not plantar flex
like this he's towards the flexed in his
toe is bent
okay I'm gonna place my hands on the
back of his ankles and as he comes down
I'm pushing down hard and I'm going to
lean forward a little bit and then lean
back okay
sometimes we'll use a foam roller if the
person has toes that are too sensitive
to being bent back by their body weight
in the partner assisted variation what
are the most common ways you see people
do these at gyms is on a lat pulldown
machine
now sometimes these pads are a little
too narrow which makes it typical for
bigger guys
but generally speaking women can do just
fine one surefire way to do this if
you're at a gym or at home is just set
up with a barbell I've got a thick bar
pad on the bar and Eric's balance pad on
the ground and make sure to have more
weight than necessary on the barbell so
it's not going to pick up so you're
gonna have more than your body weight
and I have a pair of 25 pound plates on
each side making sure the bar doesn't
move
another way to do it is off the smith
machine so same thing he just left down
a thick bark net on the bar and we'll
wait and something in front if you have
a gym like ours here at glute lab we're
doing Nordics day-in day-out with all of
our clients so it helps us to have a
dedicated nordic station this is a sword
X Hormats glute-ham race and we use it
all the time there's no setup required
you just get in and drop all right now
let's discuss common errors and false
with the Nordic
common what I see is a changing hip
angle so contrary to what most people
think most coaches will take it's only a
good Nordic camera if you're in full hip
extension or neutral and you remain that
way the whole time here at blue lab we
don't believe that the reason why if you
lean a little bit at the torso you
lengthen your hamstrings slightly it
just makes for a more productive
repetition however the caveat is you
don't change that hip angle
so here's turn is going to start out
with a bit of a lean so leaning even
more so what we want here is say this is
30 degrees of hip flexion we want to
stay at 30 degrees of hip flexion and
moving to full knee extension so here's
the right way so see how he stays hip
angle stays at 30 gets full knee
extension comes up here's the wrong way
he's going to come down and he's gonna
lean lean lean lean stop freeze see out
now he doesn't even get on the extension
so he can't even get a full hamstring
stretch in terms of knee extension but
all he did is lean more at the hip now
he's at around a 90 degree hip angle so
he changed that angle and lead to more
and what this does now is this is he
stops the rep right here and then comes
back up I will show you the wrong way
once again see how he's leaning more as
it goes down that's a big no-no another
common area that we've observed in the
Nordic is an incomplete range of motion
we want to try to get to full knee
extension at the bottom and get a full
stretch through the hamstrings sometimes
when people are progressing to a full
Nordic they'll limit the range of motion
so they can come back on their own
another way that will do this mistake is
as they perform a negative they'll use
their arms and limit that range of
motion before their thighs are flat
against the pad and that they've gotten
to fold the extension so here's what we
want to see
and the last air is inappropriate
absorption with the arms
so sometimes we see people doing almost
like a Nordic trust fall where they just
shy off and they don't use their arms to
control it so as you're coming down
we're going to put the arms out and use
them appropriately while you're
lengthening so you can control the
tension drop a more full range of motion
some people find that they're just not
prepared for a full Nordic either they
can't support their weight on the way
down or they're feeling a little bit of
pain on the back side of the knee in
that case we usually recommend that they
regress the movement a little bit until
they're prepared for that motion
one such example is with the sore necks
glute/ham roller we're going to do
single leg East Centrex to start to get
used to managing your body weight with
an eccentric contraction and another way
is to perform manual resisted eccentric
knee flexion now I'm just pushing on the
lowering phase and letting him come up
for the concentric once we've had
clients do the regressions and begin
preparing for Nordics we'll start them
out with some assisted methods
the first we call the stripper Nordic
because we're gonna use a pole notice
the distance in which he places the pole
away from him he was gonna walk his way
down
another assistant variation that we like
is the band assistant we find this extra
useful when we anchor it to a higher
point and it provides more assistance at
the bottom which is generally where
people require it the most anyways
and the last assisted method we use is
the partner assisted or manual assisted
method so starter is going to have his
hands out and easy to come down you will
use me but I'll be pushing up so he
absorbs once he gets to the very bottom
I pushed up like that and help do one
more now this requires some rhythm and
coordination between the trainer and the
client you get better over time
now let's discuss Nordic variations and
progressions
this one is known as a razor Nordic and
Brett's going to perform it with his
hips locked at 90 degrees the entire
time
notice he still gets to full extension
at the knee while keeping the hips
locked at 90 degrees one of the first
progressions that we like to focus on is
a pause rep and what we're gonna try to
do here is identify the breaking point
the point where you still exhibit a high
amount of control before you start to
lose control at the bottom we're gonna
have the person pause at that point so
he starts to descend into his negative
and wherever he feels you can he'll
cause for a full two seconds and then
proceed with control and then push back
up over time we want to see that point
become lower and lower
usually week by week and month to month
right the next progression is the pulse
method so ster is gonna come down he's
gonna touch down come up three times now
he's just he's using his hamstring as
much as possible and just using his arms
for assistance so this gives you more
time under tension in the extended range
which is the hardest part of the range
motion next up is the slow manually
resisted Nordik so what I'm going to do
here this range of motion right here is
the strong range of motion when you do a
normal Nordic you don't feel much in
this range so what I'm going to do is
push against starter but he's resisting
me as much as possible so it actually
requires a lot of force so I'm going to
push push push push push push push and
then I feel where he there's like a let
off point so Stuart came up with this
method here at glue lab we've been using
it all the time we have another enhanced
variation which I'll go over next but
this makes it more effective throughout
the whole range of motion some people
like sterner find that when you initiate
with the manual enhancement it actually
makes the lowering portion more
effective at the bottom I don't know why
that is
happens with some people now we have a
faster enhanced eccentric which may have
a better crossover to sport Brett isn't
really going to resist me at the top as
I push him down at a faster velocity
next up is my favorite variation
it's the manual resisted and assisted
method I should mention that this
doesn't replace a Nordic one thing that
makes the Nordic very effective at
creating adaptations is the fact that it
gets harder and harder as you go down
but we can use manual resistance and
assistance to kind of level out that
strength curve so it's easy in the
beginning so I'm going to apply
resistance here push push push push push
I let off he keeps going down one more
once you've progressed through all the
lowering variation this is called the
Nordic lowering exercise it's also
called the Russian ham curl but that's
another story we don't know really where
it originated I think it did originate
Russia but it's pop more popularly known
as Nordic but but we've gone over all
lowering or eccentric variations thus
far well once you get really good at
these you can actually come up on your
own and perform a full repetition now
neither sterner nor I are strong enough
to do a full repetition yet so we're
going to show you a clip of one of our
clients doing it the next progression is
using a dumbbell to enhance the
eccentric and lowering yourself down
with control dropping the dumbbell at
the bottom and coming back up on your
own
[Music]
now ideally I wouldn't have used
assistance on the way up I went down
with the dumbbell and come back up on my
own but I'm not that strong yet so there
you have it that's all about the Nordic
and parole